翻译：圈圈
翻译：幸田实果子
翻译：面条打包子
翻译：roaddog
翻译：潇湘月影
翻译：送小孩
翻译：冰蓝
时间轴：没有影子
时间轴：ans
时间轴：魔人
时间轴：sage
校对：冰蓝
后期：冰蓝
总监：冰蓝
古战场传奇
第一季 第十二集
拉里布洛克
它们就像鸟儿一样停留在空中吗
And they just stay aloft, like birds?
不  飞机机翼是静止的
Well, no. Airplane wings are stationary.
它们不会拍动
They don't flap.
你乘坐过吗
And you've ridden in one?
是的  乘坐过几次吧
Yes, several times.
我喜欢飞
I love flying.
你能飞多高
How high can you fly?
我也不清楚
Well, I don't know exactly.
空中几千英尺高肯定有的
Thousands of feet in the air, certainly.
几千英尺吗
Thousands of feet?
那么高看世界一定跟上帝看这个世界一样吧
Must have God's own view of the world from that height.
确实很壮观
It's amazing.
尤其是你第一次升空的时候
And especially the first time you go up.
一切你在地面看到的东西
I mean, everything you can see on the ground,
都渐行渐远  直到消失
it just falls away, until it disappears.
你多大了  英格兰人
How old are you, Sassenach?
我从没问过你呢
Never thought to ask.
27岁
I'm 27.
我一直以为你跟我一样大
I always thought you were about my age
或者比我年轻
or younger.
-你失望了吗  -没有
- Are you disappointed? - No.
不过
It's just that
等我40岁  你就245岁了
when I'm 40, you'll be 245.
你数学不太好啊
I think your calculations are a little off.
到了
There it is.
拉里布洛克
Lallybroch.
这就跟你经常说的一样
It's like you always said it was.
是啊
Aye.
走吧
Come.
来
那是以前了  杰米
It's behind you now, Jamie.
都过去了
It's in the past.
有谣言
There were rumors.
杜格尔之后告诉我
Dougal told me afterward
说兰德尔让珍妮怀孕生下了私生子
that Randall had got Jenny with a bastard child.
只是谣言而已
It's rumors.
是啊
Aye.
你还想继续看吗
You care to see more?
还是想进屋
Or would you rather go into the house
让我更好地娱乐一下
and offer me better entertainment?
你好
Hello.
我叫克莱尔
Hi, my name's Claire.
你是在玩苹果吗
Are you playing with the apples?
你叫什么
What's your name?
杰米
Jamie?
珍妮
Jenny.
整整四年  音信全无
Four years and no word?
这是我的小杰米
This is my wee Jamie.
这是你舅舅  宝贝
This is your uncle, mo chridhe,
你的名字就是根据他的取的
the one you're named after.
为什么
Why?
为什么根据我的名字给他取名
Why would you name him after me?
怎么了  哥哥  你病了吗
What's wrong, a-graidh? Are you ill?
难道你觉得因为那件事
Do you not think I've suffered enough
我的痛苦还不够吗
for what I let happen that...
你还让兰德尔的私生子和我同名
Ye must name Randall's bastard after me,
你是想让我在耻辱中过一辈子吗
to be a reproach as long as I live?
兰德尔的私生子
Randall's bastard?
你是指英格兰队长杰克·兰德尔吗
Jack Randall, you mean, the redcoat captain?
去找克鲁克太太吧  宝贝
Go find Mrs. Crook, my wee lamb.
我没听错吧  哥哥
Correct me, brother, if I'm wrong,
我怎么觉得
but I have a strong impression
你说我是兰德尔队长的妓女
you're saying that I played the whore to Captain Randall.
我宁愿死
I'd rather I was dead in my grave
也不愿看到我妹妹...
than see my sister brought to such...
这个又是谁的
And whose is this one?
让你为了我毁了自己我就够丢脸了  但
To have you ruin yourself for me was shame enough, but...
你又怀了一个没有父亲的私生子吗
Another one with no father to give him a name?
我们不该来的
We shouldn't have come.
杰米  要不我们先进去...
Jamie, perhaps we should all go inside--
不要让那个婊子掺和我的事
Tell that trollop to keep her neb out of my business.
她是我妻子  你对她放尊重点
She's my wife, and you will speak of her with respect.
杰米  别这样
Jamie, please.
非得让我像小时候那么对你吗
Do I have to do what I did when we were bairns?
扯住你的睾丸
Grab you by the bollocks
让你停下来听我说话
to make you stand still and listen to me?
你打算在我妻子面前羞辱我吗
Are you now trying to shame me in front of my own wife?
她是你妻子的话
Well, if she's your wife,
想必比我更熟悉你的蛋蛋吧
I imagine she's more familiar with your balls than I am.
别考验我  哥哥
Don't test me, brother.
我最后一次见你时  你浑身是血  筋疲力尽
Last I saw you, bloodied and broken,
手腕被吊在拱门上
strung up by your wrists in that archway,
让我觉得你死了
and then leaving me to think you're dead,
或者永远不再回来
or certain never to return again,
这就是你回家的态度吗
And this is how you come home?
这男孩是谁的
Whose child is the boy?
我的
Mine.
肚子里的那个也是
And that one, too.
伊恩
Ian?
你的妹夫
Yer brother-in-law.
见到你真好  杰米
It's good to see ya, Jamie.
你总是知道该怎么出场
You always knew how to make an entrance.
我们以为你死了
We thought you were dead
直到我们收到你从里奥克城堡寄来的箱子
until we received your chest from Castle Leoch.
这位是
And this would be?
那个荡妇
The trollop,
也叫克莱尔·弗雷泽
otherwise known as Claire Fraser.
珍妮  我是...
Jenny I-I'm--
该死的傻瓜
A damned fool,
四年了都没变聪明点
and no a day wiser in four years.
你喝威士忌吗
Ye drink whiskey?
能喝一两杯
I have been known to have a glass or two.
我们今天可不只要喝一两杯  克莱尔
Today, I'm thinking we'll be taking more than that, Claire.
谢谢你  伊恩  干杯
Thank you, Ian. Cheers.
兰德尔后来跟你怎么样了
What happened with Randall?
我想知道
I want to know.
我必须知道
I need to know.
那我告诉你
Then I'll tell you...
仅此一次  之后永不提起
Once... And never again.
他把你打晕之后
After he felled you...
拉着我的手
Take my hand.
我跟他进了屋
I went with him into the house.
他带我上了二楼
He took me up the stairs.
他一直在讲话
He was talking the whole way up,
但我一个字也没听进去
but I didn't hear a word he said.
我一直在想该怎么办
My mind was racing with what to do.
努力保持理智
I was just trying to keep my wits.
他领我走进卧室
He led me into the bedroom.
看着我
Look at me.
他把我扔到床上
He threw me on the bed,
然后在那儿站了一会儿
and then he stood there a minute,
自己撸
rubbing himself.
我那时还没跟男人发生过关系
I hadn't been with a man then,
但我现在知道他当时在努力
but I ken now that he was trying to...
硬起来
make himself ready.
转过去
Turn around.
我不知道为什么要笑
I don't know why.
那是我脑海中唯一想要的事情
It was the only thing that came to my mind to do,
但他不喜欢我笑  我能看出来
but he didn't like it when I laughed, and I could see that,
所以我不停地笑
so I laughed some more.
我叫你转过去  你个苏格兰贱人
I said turn around, you Scottish cunt.
等我醒来  他走了
When I woke up, he was gone.
那是我最后一次见到兰德尔队长
And that's the last I saw of Captain Randall.
你满意了
Ye satisfied?
你错了  你该跟我道歉
Ye see, you were wrong, and I'm expecting an apology.
我没说过吗
Have I no said as much?
你没说
No, you haven't.
她说得对  你该给她道歉
She's right, she deserves an apology.
这是我哥哥和我之间的事
This is between my brother and me.
我只是建议让他...
I was just suggesting that he--
我们能单独聊会儿吗
Can I see you in private for a moment?
请别介意
Excuse us.
我是你的丈夫
I'm yer husband.
你不能在我家人和佣人面前让我难堪
You mustn't embarrass me in front of my family and the servants.
你自己倒是挺会羞辱自己的
You're doing a fine enough job of that yourself.
你言辞犀利  克莱尔
You've a sharp tongue, Claire,
但也要分时间场合
but there's a time and a place for it.
那我想这由你来决定咯
Oh, and I suppose you'll be the judge of that?
在这里我需要你相信我
I need you to trust me here.
这是我的家人
This is my family,
我的土地
my land,
我的时代
my time.
我是领主  你是我的夫人
I'm laird, and you are my lady.
我们的行为举止应该配得上这种身份
We should both conduct ourselves as such.
我不是那种温驯听话的人
I'm not the meek and obedient type.
没人会犯那种错  英格兰人
Don't think anyone would ever make that mistake, Sassenach,
不过也没人会对卡伦的妻子
but then I don't think anyone would ever say the same
说那些话
of Colum's wife, either.
-利蒂希娅  -是的
- Letitia? - Aye.
坚强的女人  受人尊敬  甚至令人畏惧
Strong woman, respected, feared even,
但她从没在公开场合反驳她丈夫
but she never crossed her husband's word in public.
这会儿就我们两个  这么说吧
Now behind closed doors, let's just say
我舅舅躲过不少朝他飞来的陶器
my uncle dodged his share of crockery in his time.
小心点  领主大人
Be careful, my Laird.
我的臂力可比利蒂希娅强多了
I have a much better throwing arm than the fair Letitia.
那么
So...
你是哪里人  克莱尔
whereabouts are ye from, Claire?
我来自牛津郡
Oxfordshire originally,
但我想这里现在就是我的家
but I suppose this is now my home.
这么说你们准备留下
Ye're planning on staying then?
对
Aye.
对  我们不走了
Aye, we are.
那你被通缉的事呢
What about the price on yer head?
希望我会被免罪
I'm expecting a pardon,
桑德林罕姆公爵会帮助我
with the aid of the Duke of Sandringham.
还没被正式批准  但应该快了
It hasn't come through yet, but we're hoping it will soon.
从没想到你会这么相信英格兰人
Never thought you'd be so trusting of the English.
能麻烦你们帮我准备点洗澡的热水吗
Perhaps I could trouble you for some warm water to wash?
之前几天一直在赶路
Been a difficult few days.
你提到过有个里奥克的箱子
And you mentioned a chest from Leoch?
对
Aye.
一位叫菲茨吉本斯太太的女人送来的
It came from a woman called Mrs. Fitzgibbons.
放在楼上的客房里
It's upstairs in the spare room.
既然领主要留下
Well, since the Laird's staying,
那他应该住主卧
he should have the main bedchamber.
把我们的东西搬去北屋
Move our things to the north room.
不  你们不能因为我们换房间
No, we wouldn't dream of putting you out of your room.
毕竟那个房间是属于领主的
Well, seeing as it's the Laird's room, after all...
我去拿行李
I'll get the case.
你错过了龙卷风
You missed the whirlwind.
错过了什么
The what?
那几个仆人
The servants.
他们风卷残云般把这里收拾干净了
They tore through here like dervishes.
我转过身的功夫
I'd barely turned my back,
他们已经把珍妮和伊恩的东西都搬走了
and they'd cleared away all of Jenny and Ian's things.
这里就跟我记忆中一样
It's almost exactly how I remember it.
我父亲总把书放在那里
My father always had a book over there,
摊开在他读到的地方
open at the page he was reading.
他以前把靴子放在这儿
And he used to put his boots here.
这里藏着他的
And--and he used to keep his...
藏着他的
keep his...
他的刀
his blade.
真是把好刀
Oh, it's beautiful.
应该是维京海盗时期的
It's Viking, I think.
对
Aye.
五叶头
Five-lobed pommel.
十世纪的古董
Tenth century.
我说过
I told you.
我是被考古学家带大的
I was raised by an archeologist.
我认得刀柄上的图案
I recognize the patterns on the hilt.
这是个精美的图案
It's a fine example.
我小时候很少来这里
I'd hardly tiptoe in here as a boy,
领主的房间神圣不可侵犯
so sacred was the Laird's room.
但当他外出干活时  我会偷溜进来
But I'd slip in when he was out at the fields,
就为了能挥舞它一小会
just to hold it for a few moments.
梦想着有一天它会属于我
Dream of the day it would be mine.
现在它属于你了  杰米
It is yours now, Jamie.
是属于我们的
Ours.
是我们的
我的父亲
My father,
这地方是他一手建造的
he built this place, ye ken.
他的血与泪融入了这些石头里
His blood and sweat are in this stone.
这片土地中
This land.
而现在他的骨头也成为了这土地的一部分
And now his bones are, as well.
他们将他葬在了墓地里
They buried him out in the graveyard,
埋在我母亲
next to my mother
和我哥哥威利旁边
and my brother, Willie.
你最后一次见你父亲是什么时候
When was the last time you saw your father?
在威廉堡
It was at Fort William,
我第一次被鞭打一周之后
a week after I'd been flogged the first time.
杰米
Jamie!
父亲  您来这里干什么
Father, what are ye doing here?
来跟兰德尔队长谈谈
Having a word with Captain Randall,
看能不能救你出去
trying to see if we can get ye out.
我很抱歉闯了这么大的祸
I'm sorry for the whole damn mess.
您让我管事  结果珍妮被
Ye left me in charge, and now Jenny's--
之前的事并不是你的错
What has happened is not yer fault.
我知道你被鞭打了
I know you were flogged.
-我会没事的  -兰德尔队长在等你
- I'll be all right. - Captain Randall is waiting.
不
No.
他是我儿子
This is my son.
你们毫无怜悯之心吗
Have ye no compassion?
记得要祈祷
Remember to pray,
不论发生什么事  我都会支持你
and I'll stand by ye, no matter what happens.
你是个好孩子  儿子
Ye're a braw lad, son.
我刚见了你父亲
I just met your father.
他很担心你
He's worried about you.
当我告诉他你的指控十分严重时
I'm afraid he was disappointed when I told him
恐怕他很失望
your charges are of such a serious nature
只有收到阿盖尔公爵亲笔写的书面许可
that you cannot be bonded without a written clearance
才能将你担保出去
from the Duke of Argyll.
问题是
And the thing is,
即便他能成功拿到这份许可
even if he does succeed in getting such a clearance,
虽然可能性很小
which I doubt,
他也绝没可能及时赶回来
it would be impossible for him to make it back in time,
所以
so...
你和我一见面就交恶真的很遗憾
it's a shame that you and I have got off to such a poor start.
就在一周前
Only a week before,
他差点打死我
he'd had me flogged near to death.
我不明白  想不通他
Didn't understand, I couldna imagine
现在为什么说这话
what he was talking about now.
他又说了些其它的
And he bandied words around for a while.
他就喜欢这样
He likes to do that.
折磨自己的玩具
Likes to play with his toys.
但最后他也直说了自己
But in the end he was quite blunt about
真正想要什么
what he really wanted.
什么
Which was what?
我
Me.
很简单
It's quite simple.
向我投降
Give over to me.
交出你的身体
Make free of your body...
我就不会再鞭打你了
and there will be no second flogging.
如果你不肯
And if not...
那...
well...
我身上的鞭痕还没愈合
The first stripes were still raw on my back.
甚至碰到衣服都疼
I could scarce bear my shirt.
每次站起来
And I felt dizzy
眼前天旋地转
every time I stood up.
一想到...
The thought of...
又要再经历一次
of going through it all again,
五花大绑
being bound,
绝望无助
helpless,
等着下一鞭落下
waiting for the next lash...
我当时不甚了解  但是...
I had no real idea, of course, but...
觉得被他侵犯可能不会那么疼
I thought being buggered would be less painful
也没那么久
and be over quicker, most likely.
而且他说我当天就能被释放
And he said I'd be set free the same day,
所以
so...
我考虑了
I considered it.
但...
But...
我还能感受到我父亲在我脸颊的一吻
I could still feel my father's kiss on my cheek
一想到他会怎么想我
and thought what he would think of me.
不是被侵犯
Not the buggery.
他根本不会在乎那个  而是...
He'd no gi' that a thought or care, but...
我轻易投降
for giving in.
向那家伙屈服
For letting that man break me.
所以我办不到
So I couldn't do it.
我当时被鞭打时  杜格尔在场
Dougal was there, at the flogging.
我父亲也在  但我当时不知道
My father, too, though I didn't know it at the time.
打到中途我晕过去
I fell halfway through.
他们以为我死了
They thought I was dead.
杜格尔说
Dougal said
他轻哼了一声  直直倒了下去
he let out a small sound and dropped like a rock
再也没起来
and didn't get up again.
我没看见
I didn't see it.
没看见他去世
Didn't see him die.
没看见他被抬走
Didn't see him taken away.
没看见他下葬
Didn't see him buried.
连他的墓也没见到
Never even seen his grave.
就算你向兰德尔投降
Even if you had given in to Randall,
你觉得最后结局会有差别吗
do you really think it would have made any difference?
你不觉得他还是会
And don't you think he would have still had you
拖你去那院子  鞭打你
dragged out into that yard and flogged you
只为享受随之的病态快感吗
just for the sick pleasure it gave him?
我不知道
I'll never know.
换身衣服要那么久吗
How long does it take a person to dress?
晚饭要凉了
Supper's not going to keep.
我们该洗个澡了
We should get cleaned up.
你打理过家务吗
Have you ever run a house before?
没有
No.
那你要学习很多
Then ye'll have a lot to learn about
打理这种大宅子的事了
keeping up a place like this.
是啊
I would imagine.
听着似乎很考验人  我学得很快的
It sounds quite challenging. I'm a quick study.
你会有机会的
Ye'll get your chance.
明天就是季度结账日
Quarter day is tomorrow.
那是什么
What is that?
就像我们帮麦肯齐家族收租那样
It's like when we collected the rents for the MacKenzies,
但现在是佃户来付我们租子
but here the tenants come to us to pay.
这次结账真是及时雨
And sorely needed this quarter.
我们已经连续两年收成不佳了
We've had poor harvests two years running.
债务堆得像山一样
We're piling debt upon debt.
还是等下再说钱的事吧
Ah, we can talk about finances later.
明天我们要庆祝领主的回归
Tomorrow will be a time for celebrating the Laird's return.
听起来很公开
Sounds very public.
这样不冒险吗
Isn't that risky?
至少等到你的赦令下来吧
At least until your pardon comes through.
-不  -我们的佃户就像家人
- No. - Our tenants are like family.
没有任何人会向英格兰兵出卖杰米
Not a man, woman or child would think about betraying Jamie
无论什么代价
to the redcoats, at any price.
当然
Of course.
那我很欣慰
It's good to hear.
晚饭后我想看一眼账簿
I'll take a look at the ledgers after we've eaten.
还以为你想去父亲的墓呢
Thought you'd want to visit father's grave?
明天吧
Tomorrow.
如果他还在世  会希望你今晚就见他
If he were alive, he'd expect a visit this evening.
如果他还在世  会希望我审查账簿
If he were alive, he'd expect me to go over the ledgers
为结账日做准备
and prepare for quarter day.
那随你吧
Suit yerself then.
来点填馅卷心菜吗  克莱尔
Stuffed cabbage, Claire?
不了  谢谢
No, thank you.
-你好  -真高兴您能回来  领主
- Hello. - We're right pleased to have you back, my laird.
大家都希望您二位能在家安定下来
We hope you both bide at home for a good long while now.
我们也是  罗伯特  谢谢你
As do we, Robert. Thank you.
我给您带了个小礼物  夫人
I brought this small gift for you, mi'lady.
你真好  谢谢
Oh, how lovely, thank you.
看起来很美味
It looks delicious.
这是送给您的  夫人
I brought these for you, mi'lady.
-非常感谢  -不用客气
- Thank you so much. - You're welcome.
很漂亮
They're beautiful.
你好吗  很高兴见到你
How are ye? Good to see ye.
杰米
Jamie?
可以开始了吗
Should we get started?
好
Aye.
你好
Hello.
来摸摸
Feel.
我觉得是个男孩
I think it's a boy.
别拘束
Make yourself at home.
-你觉得是男孩吗  -嗯
- So you think it's a boy? - Yeah, I think so.
邓肯
Duncan.
娶老婆了啊
Married now?
是的  领主
Aye, my laird.
邓肯  你只还了一半钱
Duncan, this is but half of what ye owe.
抱歉  可是我们家有头牛两个月前病死了
Apologies, but we lost one of our cows to sickness two months ago.
可以下季度再还
Well, ye can settle up next quarter,
到那时你手头应该会宽裕些了
when I'm certain things'll be better.
感谢您的理解和仁慈
I appreciate your understanding and mercy.
这不算仁慈
Not mercy at all.
你父亲是个好人
Yer father was a good man.
当我还是孩子时  他就在此耕耘
Farmed this land when I was but a bairn.
钱给我
Give me that.
我不会在你有困难的时候
I'll no squeeze the last penny from you
榨干你的最后一分钱
when times are hard.
我父亲如此  我也一样
That was my father's view. Mine as well.
谢谢您  领主
Thank ye, my laird.
衷心感谢您
Thank ye, kindly.
好了  下一位
All right, who's next?
真好看
It's so pretty.
薰衣草不错  我喜欢用它提炼精油
The lavender's great. I like to make an oil from it.
晚上可以把精油涂在手腕上  像这样
You put it on your wrists at night, like this.
干杯  伙计们
Cheers, boys.
把它放回去  你个无耻的小杂种
You put that back, you cheeky wee bastard.
打扰一下
Excuse me.
我们应该没见过面
I don't believe we've met.
我是克莱尔·弗雷泽  布洛克·图拉克夫人
Claire Fraser, Lady Broch Tuarach.
我知道你是谁
I ken fine who you are.
我说了  这没你的份
I told you there'd be none fer you.
麦饼还有很多呢
There are plenty of bannocks.
他们说他娶了个英格兰人
They said he'd gone and married a Sassenach.
没错
That's correct.
需要我帮忙吗
Can I be of some assistance?
这小子只需要学会听话
Boy's just got to learn to do what he's told.
也许可以让我带他一会儿
Then maybe I can take him off your hands for a few minutes.
-为什么  -这样你就可以尽兴玩乐
- What for? - So you can enjoy yourself
不用总是看着他
without having to watch him.
跟你朋友好好玩玩
Join your friends.
别给他灌输
Just don't be filling his head
英格兰人油嘴滑舌的那一套
with any of that English claptrap.
你老实点
And you behave.
没事了
It's all right.
我们去厨房好吗
Maybe we should go to the kitchen,
给你找点吃的
find you something to eat, okay?
我想我们能找到比麦饼还好吃的东西
I think we can find you something tastier than bannocks.
这是怎么了
What have we here then?
珍妮
Jenny...
他父亲对他很粗暴
His father was being very rough with him.
后背疼吗
Is your back sore?
我们该给他洗洗  再给他吃点好的
We should get him cleaned up and something tasty to eat.
这是谁干的
Who did that?
不用你操心
Not for you to worry about.
克鲁克太太会给你找点吃的
Mrs. Crook will get you a wee bite.
是他父亲  我看见他在外面打他
It was his father. I saw him beat him outside.
麦克纳布
Macnab?
-是啊  我记得他  -打扰一下  夫人
- Yeah, I remember him. - Excuse me, mistress.
领主  来跟我喝一杯吧
M'laird, will you take a drink with me?
我们就不管管吗
Shouldn't we do something about it?
杰米
Jamie?
晚安  领主
Good night, m'laird!
不用担心我
Don't you worry about me.
大象都比你坐得轻巧
I've seen elephants sit down with less impact.
麻烦说英语
English, please.
英格兰人
Sassenach,
你现在是苏格兰人了  该学学盖尔语
now ye're a Scot, ye should work on yer Gaelic.
你去哪了
Where have you been?
跟麦克纳布出去了
Out with Macnab.
我想跟他讲理来着  结果到了最后
I tried to reason with him, but in the end I had to
还是得教他虐待和惩罚的区别
show him the difference between abuse and discipline,
用拳头
Huh, with these.
我跟他说  "罗纳德
Then I said to him, "Ronald,
"要是再让我发现你伤害你儿子
"If I ever see any evidence of yer harming your wee laddie,
你就得给布洛克·图拉克领主一个交代"
you'll have to answer to Laird Broch Tuarach,"
就是我
That's me. Huh.
是的  我知道
Yes, I know.
杰米  你一身酒气
Jamie, you reek.
你真见过大象吗
You've actually seen an elephant?
是的  还骑过一头
Yes. Rode one, too.
你一定要
Ye'll have to--
给我讲讲这事
to tell me all about it.
要犬毛吗[醒酒液]
Hair of the dog?
我觉得我需要一整只猎犬
I think I may need the whole hound.
伊恩说你昨天没有收租
Ian tells me ye didna collect the rents yesterday.
今年很艰难  你自己说的
It's been a hard year, as ye said yerself.
作为领主  我决定减轻一下佃户的负担
As laird, I decided to give my tenants some ease.
等我们入不敷出  整块领地破产以后
And how easy do ye suppose yer tenants will be when
你觉得那些佃户会有多轻松
the whole estate goes under because we canna make ends meet?
也许我们应该延期谈这事
Perhaps we should postpone this
等他舒服一点...
till he's feeling a little--
而且你又给我们添了一口人
And ye've saddled us with another mouth to feed.
你在说什么呢  珍妮
What're ye on about, Jenny?
罗比·麦克纳布
Rabbie Macnab.
他父亲把他赶了出来  拜你所赐
His father threw him out, thanks to you.
他说"既然杰米认为他能当个更好的父亲
He said, "If Jamie Fraser thinks he can be a better father,
那么他一定付得起他的抚养费"
he can damn well pay for his upkeep."
珍妮  他只是想帮助那个男孩
Jenny, he was only trying to help the boy out,
干净的衣服和薄饼并不能阻止
and clean clothes and bannocks aren't going to stop the boy
那个男孩被打
from being beaten.
你以为你们走过
Do ye think life just started
那扇门的时候  人生才开始的吗
when the two of you walked through that door?
罗比的祖母和我正在努力让罗纳德的姐姐
Rabbie's granny and I were working on Ronald's sister
收养那个男孩
to take the boy.
你掏出拳头之前就没有考虑过
Did ye not even consider talking to me before
先和我谈谈吗
you pulled out yer fists?
你觉得父亲会这样处理吗
Do ye think that's how father would have handled things?
我现在是这块领地的领主
I am the laird of this estate now,
我不需要和我的妹妹讨论如何治理这里
and I do not need to discuss the running of it with my sister.
请您原谅  布洛克·图拉克领主
Beggin' yer pardon, laird Broch Tuarach.
克鲁克太太
Mrs. Crook!
是的  领主
Yes, my laird?
这块面包尝起来就像鹅卵石做的
This bread tastes like it was made with pebbles.
磨坊无法正常运作
The mill's not working properly.
我们不得不用手磨面粉
We had to grind the flour by hand.
对此做了什么事吗
What's being done about it?
女士...  莫瑞太太...
The mistress... Mrs. Murray...
派我去找了戴维·麦克安德鲁斯修磨坊
Had me send for Davy McAndrews to fix the mill.
我亲自处理吧
I'll deal with it myself.
情况如何
How's it looking?
如果水轮在转就好多了
It'd be a damn sight better if the wheel were turning.
水闸下面一定被东西卡住了
There must be something stuck under the sluice.
我必须下去  试试能不能撬松
I'm gonna have to go down, see if I can pry it loose.
什么
What?
但是
But...
杰米
Jamie...
你会冻死的
You'll freeze to death.
很有可能
Most likely.
至少你在我的守灵式上能提供像样的薄饼了
At least ye'll be able to serve decent bannocks at my wake.
见鬼
Oh. Cack!
克鲁克夫人说那个愚蠢的笨蛋来了这里
Mrs. Crook told me the stupid fool had come up here.
珍妮
Jenny,
你现在的身体状况不该乱跑
You shouldn't be chasing around in your condition.
你没必要来找我们
There was no need for you to come after us.
有必要
Aye, there was.
别开口
Keep silent.
不能让他们知道你是英格兰人
We don't want them to know you're English.
早安  女士们
Good morrow, ladies.
早安
Good morrow.
如果你们停下来是为了吃饭
If ye're stopping for a bag of meal,
恐怕你们要失望了
I'm afraid ye'll be disappointed.
水轮眼下还没修好
The mill wheel's no working just now.
也许下次你们来时就好了
Perhaps next time ye come this way.
出了什么毛病
What's amiss, then?
你应该叫你的长官回来
Ye should call yer master back.
他不该插手自己不懂的事
He shouldna meddle in things he doesna understand.
你不用担心  太太
Oh, you've no cause for worry, missus.
下士的父亲在汉普郡也有座磨坊
Corporal's father has a wheat mill in Hampshire.
他对水轮可以说是了若指掌
What he doesn't know about water wheels would fit in me shoe.
这样没用  我得下去
No help for it. I'll have to go under
看看被什么东西卡住了
and see what's holding it.
瞧瞧
Look at that!
不知道是什么卡在里面
Wonder what was stuck in it.
一件完好的衬衫
A perfectly good shirt.
这东西怎么会卡到水轮里
How on earth did that get stuck into the mill?
这里是苏格兰  长官
It's Scotland, sir.
女士们
Ladies.
衷心感谢你  先生
Thank you kindly, sir.
驾
Hee-up!
杰米
Jamie!
愿神圣的迈克尔保护我们
Blessed Michael defend us.
你在做什么  你这笨蛋
What the hell were ye doing, ye?
你难道一点也没长大吗
Have ye not grown up a bit?
珍妮  你能不能...
Jenny, will ye...
你能不能转过头  我好出来
will ye please turn around when I try to get out?
免得我的老二被冻断
Before my cock snaps off.
她在这里做什么
What the hell was she doing here?
她听说英格兰巡逻军要来
Heard about the redcoat patrol.
她只是想来警告你
She was just trying to warn you.
你是个夜猫子啊
So you're a night owl, are ye?
我想是的
Yes, I suppose I am.
珍妮跟百灵鸟一样
Jenny's up with the lark,
但我自己也是夜猫子
but I've always been an owl myself.
这是珍妮吗
Is this Jenny?
是的  那些是她的鸟
Aye. Those were her birds.
有哪只鸟瘸了腿或者翅膀受伤了
Any time one was found wi' a lame leg or a broken wing,
她就会治愈它  让鸟儿从她手里吃东西
she'd have it healed and eating from her hand.
你很惊讶她还有温柔的一面吗
You surprised she has a gentle side?
当然不是啦
No, of course not.
也许有点吧
Perhaps a little.
她是弗雷泽家的人
She's a Fraser.
他们的心胸宽广  心肠柔软
Their hearts are as big and soft
十分固执
as their heads are thick and strong.
我拄着一根木头假腿从法国回来时
It was Jenny who took care of me after I returned from France
是珍妮照顾了我
with a stump of wood.
杰米告诉我
Jamie told me you lost it
你俩在法国打仗时  你丢了腿
while the both of you were fighting in France.
这没让我走慢多少
It doesn't slow me down much.
一天结束的时候会有点疼
It aches a wee bit towards the end of the day.
你试过荚蒾或者水蓼吗
Have you tried guelder rose or water pepper?
我没有试过水蓼
I've no tried the water pepper, no.
我愿意帮你做一些
Well, I'd be happy to make some for you.
谢谢
Thank you.
杰米说你是个医生
Jamie said you were a healer.
你之前见过残疾人吗
Ye've seen mangled men before?
不幸的是  我见过很多
Yes, many, unfortunately.
杰米没有
Jamie hadn't.
一开始他看见我这样时大吃一惊
It shocked him to see me like this at first.
他想隐藏  但我知道
He tried to hide it, but I knew.
这不重要
Ah, no matter.
他带我回到苏格兰  珍妮让我重获新生
He brought me back to Scotland, and Jenny made me whole again.
所以你才娶了她吗
Is that why you married her?
你觉得我有选择权吗
Ye think I had any choice in the matter?
有天我在野外修补栅栏时
She came up to me out in the field one day,
她来找我
while I was mending a fence.
我身上都是泥土
I was covered wi' muck,
而她站在那里  像是满是蝴蝶的灌木丛
and her, standing there like a bush covered wi' butterflies.
她说  我不记得她的原话了
She says--well, I dinna ken exactly what she said,
但是最后是她吻我  说着
but it ended with her kissing me, and saying,
好吧  我们在圣马丁节结婚
"Fine, we'll be married on St. Martin's day."
我当时还在给她解释我们为什么
And I was still explaining to her why we couldna do
不能做这种事
any such thing
结果发现自己站在牧师面前说
when I found myself in front of a priest saying,
我愿意娶你  珍妮特
"I take thee, Janet."
她是个了不起的女人  对吧
She's an extraordinary woman, isn't she?
是啊  当她不是个直接  固执
Aye, when she's not being an outright, stubborn-headed,
讨厌的倔强女人的时候
pain-in-the-arse mule.
弗雷泽家的人啊
Frasers.
一旦他们坚定立场  就不会移动半点
Once they've dug their heels in, there's no budging them,
当他们发怒时
and you don't want to get between them
你可不想去劝架
when their danders are up.
你怎么应付过来的
How do you manage?
这个嘛
Well...
你可以拽他们的绳子
Ye can tug on their rope
也可以从后面踢他们一下
or give them a wee kick in their backside.
他们可能会动
And they might move,
你也可能惹麻烦上身
or ye might get bit for your trouble.
然后呢
And then what?
更用力地踢
Kick them harder.
真好  现在你注意到我了
Good. Now I have your attention.
你要听我说
And you're going to listen to me.
我嫁的不是拉里布洛克的领主
I did not marry the laird of Lallybroch.
而是杰米  自从我们来这里之后
I married Jamie, but I haven't seen much of him
我没见过他多少次
since we walked through the gates of this place.
-我就是那样  既然...  -我在说话呢
- That's who I am, now that-- - I am speaking,
等我说完了你才能说
and you can talk when I'm finished.
你父亲去世了  杰米
Your father's dead, Jamie,
但如果他还在
but if he were here,
他肯定会因为你的行为而鞭打你
I wager he'd give you a thrashing for the way you've been acting.
你在扮演别的人
You're trying to be someone you're not,
在这个过程中  你伤害了剩下
and in the process you're wrecking the family
那些家人的心
that you do have left.
如果你不小心点  你也会失去他们的
And if you're not careful, you're going to lose them, too.
珍妮
Jenny.
让我吓了一跳
Gave me a start.
你以为是鬼吧
Thought it was a ghost for a minute, did ye?
-珍妮  我...  -杰米  我...
- Jenny, I-- - Jamie, I--
请让我先说
Let me speak first, please.
这是佃户的租金
That's the rent from the tenants.
我想也许我能和罗比的姑妈聊聊
And I thought perhaps I could speak to Rabbie's aunt, so...
就算她接纳了他
Even if she had taken him in,
我觉得也不会维持很久的
I don't think it would have lasted.
她已经有太多孩子了
She's a frachety woman with too many bairns as it is.
他可以去更好的地方
This is a better place for him.
父亲也会这么想的
Father would have thought so, too.
是啊
Aye.
我没先问你是不对的  我对此很抱歉
I was wrong not to consult you, and I'm sorry for it.
真心的
Truly.
我以后会改的
I hope to do it different in future.
是我误会了你  我好羞愧
I'm the one who's wronged you, and I'm so ashamed.
误会了什么
Of what?
父亲去世之后
Ever since father died...
我内心的阴暗部分觉得他的死是你的错
A small dark part of me has blamed you for his death.
他们告诉我威廉堡发生的事后
When they told me what happened at Fort William,
兰德尔亲自拿鞭子抽了你
that Randall flogged ye himself,
父亲看到那一幕才去世的
And that seeing that is what killed father,
我想着你一定是做了什么坏事
I thought you must have done something
这是你自己找的
to bring it upon yerself.
信口胡言  或者
Shot yer mouth off, or
做出没有考虑后果的行为
acted without thinking of the consequences,
你这辈子都是这样
as ye have done all yer life.
但是在磨坊池塘的时候
But then out at the mill pond,
当我看到你背后的伤疤
when I saw the scars on yer back,
抽你的鞭子是如此的
scars made by a lash laid down wi' such
愤怒...
fury--
你以后不用担心了
You dinna fash yerself about it anymore.
是因为我  因为我兰德尔才这样打你的
It was me. It's my fault that Randall beat ye so.
你不知道自己在说什么
You dinna ken what you're saying.
我知道
But I do.
兰德尔来这里的那天
That day-- that day when Randall came here,
他带我去楼上时
when he took me upstairs--
如果我没有讽刺他
if I hadn't mocked him that way,
如果我让他得偿所愿
if I--if I'd given him what he wanted
他不会那样打你的
he wouldn't have treated you like he did.
然后父亲...
And then father--
我的妹妹  别
Mo chridhe, no.
别这样
Don't.
我在威廉堡的确惹毛了兰德尔
I did anger Randall at Fort William,
我过去四年里
and I've spent the past four years of my life
都将父亲的死怪到自己头上
blaming myself for father's death because of it.
但现在你更聪明了吗
But now ye know better?
是的
Aye.
的确如此
Hmm. Aye, I do.
我知道那不是你的错
I know it's not yer fault.
也不是我的
Nor mine, either.
那人心里住着恶魔  没人能影响
There's a devil in that man that no one can influence.
唯一该为害死父亲负责的人
The only one responsible for putting father in his grave
就是杰克·兰德尔
is Jack Randall.
知道吗
Aye?
但我的确觉得很烦恼
It does trouble me, though,
知道你为了拯救我而顺从他
knowing ye went with him to save me,
知道他也许会伤害你
knowing he might harm ye.
为了让你躲过一劫  我很乐意去死
I would have gladly died to spare ye.
如果你的生命可以来换我的名声
And if yer life is a suitable exchange for my honor,
告诉我我的名声为什么不能换你的生命
tell me why my honor's not a suitable exchange for yer life?
或者你是说  我爱你
Or are ye telling me that I may not love ye
不如你爱我那么多  因为如果你是这意思
as much as ye love me? Because if ye are,
杰米·弗雷泽  我现在就会告诉你不是那样的
Jamie Fraser, I'll tell you right now it's not true.
不
No.
欢迎回家
Welcome home,
布洛克·图拉克领主
Laird Broch Tuarach.
来吧
Come.
你说布洛克·图拉克的意思是"朝北的塔"
You said Broch Tuarach means "North facing tower."
是的
Aye.
那座塔是圆形的  没有朝向哪边
Well, it's round. It doesn't have a face.
这个嘛
Well...
门是对着北边的
The door faces north.
弗雷泽家的人啊
Frasers.
我开始感觉
I'm beginning to feel like...
我...
like I...
我真正属于这里
like I actually belong here.
大概是第一次
I knew
看到你的时候
ye belonged here,
我就知道
with me,
你属于这里  应该和我在一起
almost since the first time I laid eyes on ye.
那是我同意娶你的原因之一
That's one of the reasons I agreed to marry ye.
虽然不是主要的原因
Though not the main one.
主要的原因是什么
Then what was the main one?
因为我想要你  胜过我生命中的一切
Because I wanted you more than I ever wanted anything in my life.
自从我摔下马
Right from that moment I fell off the horse and...
在黑暗中醒来  看着你的脸
woke up in the dark looking up at your face.
然后我们一起骑马
Then there was that long ride together,
你可爱的圆屁股压在我的大腿之间
with that lovely round arse wedged tight between my thighs,
坚硬的头撞着我的胸膛
and that rock-solid head thumping me in the chest.
所以你同意娶我
That's why you agreed to marry me,
因为我的圆屁股和坚硬的头吗
because of my round arse and my rock-solid head?
是啊
Hmm.
我一看见你就想要你  但是
I wanted ye from the first moment I saw ye. But...
我爱过你
I loved ye
在里奥克第一晚时  你在我怀里哭泣
when ye wept in my arms that first night at Leoch.
但现在  我
But now I...
我每天醒来  发现
I wake up every day, and I find that
我爱你胜过昨天
I love you more than I did the day before.
我爱你
I love you.
-保持冷静  小伙子  -你有什么权力
- Keep calm now, lad. - What right do you come
来这栋房子
into this house without--
我听够了你这种人说的话了
I've heard enough from the likes of you.
现在你保持安静  我的朋友
Now you stay silent as a lamb, my friend...
不然这位可爱的女士会擦洗地板上
or this lovely lass is gonna be scrubbing yer brains
你的脑浆
off the floor.